<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>connor soltas</title>
    <link>http://csoltas.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on connor soltas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 23:06:16 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://csoltas.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>rethinking onboarding</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/glidera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 23:06:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/glidera/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-does-this-thing-do-anyway:6a898cf7393fef36fc5fd1f2fdc0d321&#34;&gt;what does this thing do, anyway?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike, Mohammed, and Dave thought &lt;a href=&#34;http://glidera.io&#34;&gt;their startup Glidera&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s web app looked bad. When I asked why, they couldn&amp;rsquo;t articulate what about it didn&amp;rsquo;t appeal to them, or what they would change. It just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel hip or modern to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They brought me in to give the Glidera web app a &amp;ldquo;facelift,&amp;rdquo; as they put it. So the four of us spent over an hour in one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://techstars.com/&#34;&gt;Techstars&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; conference rooms, talking through their design gripes&amp;mdash;some large and abstract, others incredibly specific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/glidera-casestudy1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I listened, I also tried to piece together what a facelift would do for their company. Sure, their app didn&amp;rsquo;t fit my personal aesthetics, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t the target user. Their core business wasn&amp;rsquo;t a web interface for consumers&amp;mdash;it was a proprietary API for their partners: Bitcoin wallet developers. Curious, I asked, &amp;ldquo;Who actually needs to use the site? What does this thing do, anyway?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The site&amp;rsquo;s just for end-users to connect their bitcoin wallet to us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That one comment changed everything about the project. What they said meant that once the end-user got her account set up on Glidera&amp;mdash;in effect connecting a bitcoin wallet to Glidera&amp;rsquo;s API&amp;mdash;then everything was good; the user was done and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t need to use the Glidera web app again unless there were problems with her bitcoin wallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the site needed to be fantastic at just one thing: onboarding users. That was all it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows form follows function. Ideally, that means any quest to solve ugliness should start with a search for brokenness. It rarely happens that way, and sometimes for good reason&amp;mdash;it&amp;rsquo;s cheaper and faster to tweak colors and fonts than to tease out underlying design problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Glidera had time and wanted to prioritize design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went full-bore. Knowing that the web app basically had one feature lent an entirely different perspective on the problem. The app&amp;rsquo;s division across four pages seemed totally unnecessary, and even confusing for users who weren&amp;rsquo;t already keenly aware of what the app was supposed to help them accomplish. It didn&amp;rsquo;t guide them through the only feature that mattered to it: setup. And it certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t reward them for completing setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shifting-gears:6a898cf7393fef36fc5fd1f2fdc0d321&#34;&gt;shifting gears&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I focused on a new question: What would an app that existed solely to have the easiest, most rewarding setup process imaginable look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came back to the Glidera team suggesting they scrap the front-end and rebuild it as a simple one-page app. They had only asked for a facelift, but I responded that the reason the site looked bad was that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t actually designed to do its purpose. Its multiple sections didn&amp;rsquo;t encourage users to complete signup&amp;mdash;they distracted users with content that wasn&amp;rsquo;t useful until setup was complete. And the setup page itself added to the confusion&amp;mdash;it wasn&amp;rsquo;t clear that the setup process had to be completed in a specific order, or that, at any given point in the process, the user had a &amp;ldquo;next step&amp;rdquo; waiting for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the desktop version of the app, I turned the setup steps into a horizontal timeline that clearly indicated your next step in the process. The app also suggested its buy/sell functionality below in a non-distracting way. Clicking the &amp;ldquo;next step&amp;rdquo; node on the timeline would trigger a modal with a simple form and a huge green checkmark, celebrating each step you completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/glidera-casestudy2.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/glidera-casestudy3.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/glidera-casestudy4.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you finished setup, the timeline itself would vanish entirely. Then you&amp;rsquo;d only see three buttons on the upper-right that allowed you to manage or edit your information. You could also buy or sell bitcoin directly through the web app, but since that wasn&amp;rsquo;t the app&amp;rsquo;s intended purpose, it stayed low on the page, almost below the fold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They liked the idea, and we ran with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/glidera-casestudy5.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mobile-too:6a898cf7393fef36fc5fd1f2fdc0d321&#34;&gt;mobile, too&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least in some abstract sense, an ideal onboarding process looks different on mobile from on a desktop. If Glidera was to optimize onboarding for mobile, too, their site couldn&amp;rsquo;t just be a normal responsive site. It would have to &amp;ldquo;respond&amp;rdquo; into a format that felt almost native&amp;mdash;like the best mobile sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since mobile users constituted a significant proportion of their new signups, I spent time tailoring the mobile site experience to make it even better than the desktop equivalent. The end result split the setup steps across five different, super-simple screens, navigated horizontally like intro screens in a native app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/glidera-casestudy6.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-ui-kit:6a898cf7393fef36fc5fd1f2fdc0d321&#34;&gt;the ui kit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The completed project consisted of a copy/paste-able UI kit, written with HTML/CSS/JS, including all the different front-end elements Glidera would need to build out the new web app, both for desktop and mobile browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>designers without borders</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/specless/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 23:04:43 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/specless/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-context:7c9e24799cf16c189e65838d6a517cec&#34;&gt;some context&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designers of online ad campaigns have to think inside the box. That is, their tools constrain them to canvases whose fixed dimensions don&amp;rsquo;t reflect the near-infinite variety of proportions their ad, once published on the web, will eventually take on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a problem for them because most designers don&amp;rsquo;t know how to code their ad to respond under different aspect ratios. They just have to design a ton of variations one-by-one, then share all those with developers. Which takes time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gospecless.com&#34;&gt;Specless&lt;/a&gt; solves that. Their founders Steve and Shashank brought me in to do a ground-up redesign of Specless&amp;rsquo;s flagship enterprise web app&amp;mdash;a design tool that writes code for the ad automatically, allowing ad designers to create just one ad for all possible shapes and sizes, and visualize precisely how it&amp;rsquo;ll look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy1.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;big-questions:7c9e24799cf16c189e65838d6a517cec&#34;&gt;big questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out the problem is really hairy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge fundamentally isn&amp;rsquo;t to design a nicer experience for creatives. It&amp;rsquo;s to make the front-end coding framework that underpins context-aware ads into something that&amp;rsquo;s no less visually intuitive than Photoshop. If the app itself can get designers to think like front-end developers (whether they know it or not), then the automatically-generated code will be simpler and it will behave better in a wider array of situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is hard because it means uniting the way designers work with the way developers think. Traditionally these are seen as polar opposites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody tells you where the line between &amp;ldquo;not enough&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;too much&amp;rdquo; abstraction is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the app would have to encourage designers to think about hierchical &lt;a href=&#34;http://cascade-framework.com/&#34;&gt;Cascade&lt;/a&gt; concepts like &amp;ldquo;flowlanes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;breakpoints.&amp;rdquo; But should it force these concepts to the fore, at the expense of a simple interface? It would have to be a graphics editor without defined canvas boundaries. But should it display one canvas, or several&amp;mdash;as it really is? It would have to convey branching conditional logic without outright teaching designers how to code. But how deep down the rabbit hole should the app push them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy3.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I figured as long as I could nail the few genuinely tricky interface questions, then the rest of the tool could parrot a stripped-down Photoshop&amp;mdash;making for a mostly familiar experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;familiar-solutions:7c9e24799cf16c189e65838d6a517cec&#34;&gt;familiar solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of a month I met every few days with Steve, Shashank, and their lead frontend developer Michael. I&amp;rsquo;d storyboard the wireframes in their most recent state&amp;mdash;and the three of them, usually Steve, the CEO, would call out issues as we went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making branched logic visual seemed like a dead-end, so at first, I tried to avoid designs that wore the full complexity of Cascade on their sleeve. I pretended breakpoints and flowlanes were equivalent concepts (when really the former is always a child of the latter), and I designed digital &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slide_rule&#34;&gt;slide rules&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://lumberjocks.com/assets/pictures/reviews/32463.jpg&#34;&gt;squares&lt;/a&gt; as digital analogues of flexible measurement devices users might already be familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy4.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcome looked okay (if somewhat heavy-handed), but Steve wanted something that more transparently matched the way the code would actually be generated. The app needed to be honest about the code it wrote, we agreed. Flowlanes were flowlanes and breakpoints were breakpoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, back to the drawing board. Instead, I turned to familiar digital tools as control analogues. Stacked &amp;ldquo;timelines&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;playheads&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;borrowed from video editing, with which designers might be even more familiar&amp;mdash;provided a simpler solution that more accurately reflected the ways CSS rules can overwrite one another. To create a new breakpoint, the user could just click the &amp;ldquo;+&amp;rdquo; where the rulers intersected and drag a new breakpoint across the ruler. Moving between breakpoints and flowlanes was easy, too, since big swaths of the canvas or ruler could be activated as giant buttons. And adding animation/interactivity was also straightforward&amp;mdash;you just opened the drawer beneath the layers panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy9.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The completed project was an &lt;a href=&#34;https://invisionapp.com/&#34;&gt;InVision&lt;/a&gt; workflow showing how the new product could reproduce Specless&amp;rsquo;s latest client project&amp;mdash;a huge responsive ad for Netflix, which took 2-3 days of hand-coding&amp;mdash;in about 5-10 minutes. Steve and the Specless team were thrilled with the result, went on to a successful fundraise, and began immediately building out the redesign of their new flagship web app in testable pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy6.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy7.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/img/specless-casestudy8.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>argument or story?</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/navipoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 23:03:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/navipoint/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:a364410aaab37cb58d171198cd16a240&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>how to cure fomo</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/hooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 23:02:29 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/hooks/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:409af6da70793fd9c8fb7707d7ac6132&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a theory of nametags</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/techstars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:59:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/techstars/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:5ee1c4c39b0c65e9a2d6d57879ed9e79&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>i went from bad to okay</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/reqwip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:58:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/reqwip/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:142b3875fc3e31d8c6b24bbfc25b316e&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>what mobile was meant to be</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/gazoo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:57:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/gazoo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:6c1682f24daa5efe263743709efa626d&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>branding a community</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/pushpin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:56:30 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/pushpin/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:3956dd8abfa2b2bf5f3b220a5394e6d5&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>perception and reality</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/safety/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:54:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/safety/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:fe9de731fa23cdbe5db01ec4e22d6b23&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>demo day, sumo style</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/seedsumo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:52:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/seedsumo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:c144cfb3e0b429b2d01ad09c8c270951&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>another demo-day deck</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/fanout/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:45:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/fanout/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:6f5432b809c3c4a2a5c618aaf6120a44&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>for businesses that deliver</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/routific/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 22:41:55 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/case-study/routific/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;under-construction:1a0bce8da8ebeee467c9231d6668bced&#34;&gt;Under construction!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check again soon for the case study. &lt;a href=&#34;http://csoltas.github.io/../..&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to return to the full project list.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kpcb design project</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/kpcb-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 20:29:01 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/kpcb-design/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>uber design project</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/uber-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 20:29:01 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/uber-design/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>http://csoltas.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 19:07:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://csoltas.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-m-a-student-at-the-university-of-chicago-studying-applied-math-and-computer-science:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;I’m a student at the University of Chicago studying applied math and computer science.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow I ended up doing product design and software development &lt;a href=&#34;http://linkedin.com/in/connorsoltas&#34;&gt;for tech companies and startups&lt;/a&gt;. This website is about those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also help run my school’s major tech entrepreneurship community, &lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.uchicago.edu&#34;&gt;Edge&lt;/a&gt;, by putting on events, coordinating UChicago’s student startup accelerator, and promoting the growing student entrepreneurship scene on campus and around Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>